just by watching them listen to music?
仅仅通过观察一个人听音乐，就能了解他/她多少信息？
Early on in The Secret Agent, there's a
在电影《秘密特工》的开头，有一个
scene where Armando, played by Wagner
场景是瓦格纳·莫拉饰演的阿曼多在
into a new apartment. At this stage in
新公寓安顿下来后就做了这件事。 在影片的这个阶段
the film, we don't know much about who
，我们对
this guy is or his backstory. So, we're
这个人是谁以及他的背景故事知之甚少。 所以，我们正在
looking for anything that might give us
寻找任何可能给我们提供
a clue.
线索的东西。
Let's look at what Moura gives us
让我们来看看莫拉
through this performance in this moment.
在这一刻通过这场比赛带给我们什么。
Right after he sits [music] down, it's
他一坐下来听音乐，就
like you can see a thought wash over
好像能看到某种思绪在
him.
他脑海中闪过。
We don't know what this is, but it
我们不知道这是什么，但它
obviously absorbs him.
显然让他沉迷其中。
&gt;&gt; [music]
[音乐]
&gt;&gt; The way he seems to zone out and
他似乎会走神，
disappear from the room as if he's not
从房间里消失，好像根本没在
even listening to the music makes me
听音乐一样，这让我
think he's remembering something.
觉得他好像在回忆什么。
Whatever he's reflecting on, there's a
无论他在思考什么，其中都蕴含着某种
weight to it that reveals some kind of
沉重的情感，透露出一种
sadness. Then, for a moment, just when
悲伤。 然后，就在这种
the emotion seems like it might break
情绪似乎要
through, it's as if he tries to push it
爆发的时候，他好像想把它推开，让
away and pull himself out of the
自己从
reflection, but he can't. Or maybe
倒影中抽离出来，但他做不到。 或许他
something else crosses his mind and he's
脑子里闪过别的事情，然后又
lost again.
迷失了方向。
Then, this other thing appears.
然后，又出现了另一个东西。   在
midst of the heaviness. Finally mixed
沉重的情绪中，闪现出一丝幸福的光芒。 最后，
with the happiness, it looks like he's
喜悦之中，他似乎在
blinking away tears before he pulls
眨眼间抹去泪水，然后才振作起来，从沉思中
himself together and breaks from this
回过神来
reflection. We won't learn the details
。 直到很久以后我们才能了解
of his backstory until much [music]
他的背景故事的细节
later, but this early piece of
，但这段早期的
performance communicates the complicated
表演传达了
weight of what this character is
这个角色所
carrying. And more than that, gives us a
背负的复杂沉重的负担。 不仅如此，它还给了我们一个
moment to connect the actual emotion of
机会去体会
this character's story. What's
这个角色故事中真正的情感。
particularly striking to me about this
这段
piece of performance is the conflict and
表演最让我印象深刻的是其中存在的冲突和
nuance that is present. [music]
微妙之处。  [音乐]
It's not a huge feat for an actor to sit
对于演员来说，
by themselves and conjure an emotion,
独自坐着并唤起某种情绪并不难，
but to do so in a way that tells a
但要以一种能够讲述
larger story about what the character is
角色经历的更宏大故事的方式来做到这一点，而
going through besides just they're sad,
不仅仅是让他们感到悲伤，这就
requires an actor that is particularly
需要演员对
the character and the story. And who
角色和故事的情感世界有特别的了解。 谁又
knows how to find a way within
知道如何在内心深处找到一种方式，用
themselves to authentically [music]
音乐真诚地
express that. Even more impressively,
表达这种情感呢？ 更令人印象深刻的是，
who knows how to do that with such a
谁能做到如此
level of restraint.
克制？
If you look at the acting Oscar winners
如果你看看过去一年奥斯卡表演奖的获奖者
from this past year, you might notice a
，你可能会注意到一个
pattern.
规律。
&gt;&gt; [screaming]
[尖叫]
&gt;&gt; Sean Penn's Lockjaw is one of the most
肖恩·潘饰演的洛克乔是
Looney Tunes performances [music] I've
我在近期电影中见过的最像乐一通动画的表演之一 [音乐]
seen in recent film. And I don't mean
。 我这么说并非出于
that as an insult. It's genuinely
侮辱。 仅凭人体就能
impressive to see someone craft such a
塑造出如此
cartoonish character with just the human
卡通化的角色，这着实令人印象深刻
body. Lockjaw is like the physical
。  Lockjaw 就像是
embodiment of pure seething [music] rage
纯粹的、沸腾的[音乐]愤怒的具象化身，
ready to burst at the seams at any
随时准备爆发
moment. But it would be hard to say that
。 但很难说
this character is [music] subtle.
这个角色（音乐）很微妙。
&gt;&gt; [screaming]
[尖叫]
&gt;&gt; Then you have Jessie Buckley in Hamnet
然后还有杰西·巴克利在《哈姆内特》中的表演，
who is fully tapped into guttural
她完全展现了内心深处的
emotion. [music]
情感。  [音乐]
It's a totally uninhibited performance
这是一场完全不受拘束的表演，
that shamelessly embraces human emotion
毫不掩饰地展现了人类情感的
at its dramatic extremes.
极端表现。
&gt;&gt; [music]
[音乐]
&gt;&gt; So I had to walk all the way across town
所以我不得不步行穿过整个城镇才到
to get here.
这里。
&gt;&gt; And of course Amy Madigan in Weapons
当然，艾米·马迪根在《武器》
&gt;&gt; [music]
（音乐）中
&gt;&gt; was almost unrecognizable, transforming
几乎让人认不出来，她把
herself into something both clown-like
自己变成了一个既像小丑
and garishly sinister.
又俗艳邪恶的角色。
&gt;&gt; Who made the complaint?
谁提出的投诉？
&gt;&gt; Perfectly walking the tightrope [music]
完美地游走在
between goofy absurdity and something
滑稽荒诞和
genuinely terrifying.
真正恐怖之间的钢丝上（音乐）。
And finally you have Michael B. Jordan
最后，迈克尔·B·乔丹为
the same film.
同一部电影中的两个角色注入了情感深度和微妙之处（音乐）。
I liked all of these performances.
我喜欢所有这些表演。
[music] I respect the craft involved in
[音乐] 我尊重
these roles. I've been fans of these
这些角色所涉及的技艺。 多年来我一直是这些演员的粉丝，我
think any of them are undeserving of the
认为他们所
recognition they received. But it's
获得的认可都是实至名归的。 但
often said that the Oscars tend to award
人们常说，奥斯卡奖往往更倾向于表彰
most acting over best acting and it's
表演次数最多的演员，而不是最佳演员，而
very hard not to see this year's winners
今年的获奖者也
as an affirmation of that bias. But I
印证了这种偏见。 但我
often find subtle layered performances
常常发现，细腻而富有层次感的表演与
affecting than the big swings,
大幅度的情感波动、
transformations, or bold displays of
转变或大胆的
emotion. For example, while Sean Penn's
情感表达一样引人入胜，有时甚至更令人感动。 例如，虽然肖恩·潘饰演的
Lockjaw was entertainingly cartoonish
洛克乔（Lockjaw）滑稽有趣
and fresh, why do we judge it as
、别具一格，但为什么我们认为它
necessarily more deserving of an award
一定
than Benicio Del Toro's stoic and firm,
比贝尼西奥·德尔·托罗饰演的沉稳坚定、
yet still warm, sensei.
却又温暖的师父更值得获奖呢？   别突然消失
&gt;&gt; Don't go dark on me, Bob.
，鲍勃。
chops to craft this character, who
塑造这样一个角色，既要符合
absurdity of the Thomas
托马斯·品
Pynchon-inflicted world of one battle
钦笔下荒诞无稽的战争世界
after another,
，又要让他
yet who still feels like a lived-in,
感觉像是一个活生生的、
fully realized human with a life and
完整的人，
history that exists outside the film? Or
拥有电影之外的生活和历史，难道不需要同样高超的演技吗？ 或者，
how do we judge the quality of those two
我们如何评判这两位演员的表演质量，
performances against the subtle
以及
intensity that Regina Hall brings to her
雷吉娜·霍尔
performance in the film with very little
在电影中
screen time?
戏份不多却展现出的微妙而强烈的表演呢？
&gt;&gt; Baby, don't be scared.
宝贝，别害怕。
&gt;&gt; For me personally, this scene was one of
对我个人而言，这一幕是
the most emotionally gripping in the
整部电影中最扣人心弦的场景之一
film.
。   《
&gt;&gt; Green Acres,
绿野仙踪》、《
Beverly Hillbillies, and Hooterville
贝弗利山庄》和《胡特维尔
Junction.
枢纽》。
&gt;&gt; Hall's character shows up out of the
霍尔饰演的角色突然出现，
blue to rescue Chase Infinity's
救下了
character, who she hasn't met before,
她之前从未见过的蔡斯·英菲尼迪饰演的角色，
and it's a more complicated acting task
这
than it might seem at face value. In one
比表面看起来要复杂得多。 在
short exchange, they need to establish a
短短的一次交流中，他们需要建立
sense of trust and do so in a way that
信任感，并且要以一种
makes it feel actually believable that
让人觉得可信的方式，让
this teenager would run away with this
这个十几岁的女孩真的会跟这个
strange adult she's never met. And both
她从未见过面的陌生成年人私奔。 两位
actors meet the challenge more than
演员都出色地完成了挑战
adequately. The sense of urgency,
。
trustworthiness, and warmth that Hall is
霍尔
able to express mostly with her voice in
在这场戏中主要通过声音表达出的紧迫感、可信度和温暖感，足以打动人心
this scene more than sells it.
。
&gt;&gt; I'm here to help, but we have to leave
我来帮忙，但我们必须
here right away.
马上离开这里。
Look, I knew your mom
我认识你
and your dad.
爸妈。
&gt;&gt; And Infinity, who's acting in her first
而首次担任重要角色的英菲尼迪，台词
major role, matches her with very little
不多，却与她
dialogue. I found the scene to be moving
配合默契。 我
both times I watched the film, and my
两次观看这部电影时都觉得这个场景很感人，我对
impression of Hall's performance in this
霍尔在这个场景中的表演印象
scene was so strong that when I was
非常深刻，以至于当我
reflecting on it to make this video, I
回想这个场景并制作这个视频时，我
could have sworn we got a close look at
发誓我们
her face in this scene, but we never do,
在这个场景中看到了她的脸部特写，但实际上并没有，
which is all the more impressive.
这反而更令人印象深刻。
&gt;&gt; Okay, let's go.
好了，我们走吧。
&gt;&gt; Her work throughout the film is a master
她在整部电影中的表现堪称
class in packing a punch with very
大师级，在极
little time on screen. But I do get why
短的出场时间内就展现出了强大的感染力。 但我理解为什么规模
the bigger, showier performances tend to
更大、更炫目的表演往往会
get more nominations and win more
获得更多提名和赢得更多
awards. In an environment where all of
奖项。 在如今这个媒体信息铺天盖地、争夺我们注意力的环境下，
us, Academy voters included, are
包括学院评委在内的所有人都被各种
overwhelmed with media that's competing
媒体信息淹没
for our attention. It's often the
。 往往是那些规模
bigger, bolder performances that tend to
更大、更精彩的表演更容易
catch our attention and stick in our
吸引我们的注意力，并让我们
minds. On top of that, it's not as if an
印象深刻。 此外，
Oscar win is determined by some
奥斯卡奖的评选并非基于某种
objective standard of quality, something
客观的质量标准，而
art. Instead, it has as much to do with
艺术领域甚至根本不可能存在这样的标准。 相反，它与
crafting a marketing campaign that tells
精心策划一场营销活动密切相关，这场活动旨在讲述
a story about why this person deserves a
为什么这个人
win at this moment. And the performances
此刻值得获得胜利。
where the work the actor put in is more
演员付出的努力在表演中显得更加
apparently obvious tend to feed those
显而易见，这往往会助长这些
narratives. At the end of the day, I'm
叙事。 说到底，我
not upset at the big showy performances.
并不反感那些盛大的表演。
I just love subtle performance, and
我非常喜欢含蓄的表演方式，而且
since I've talked about this before, I
因为我之前也谈到过这一点，我
know a lot of you do as well. So, I want
知道你们很多人也喜欢。 所以，我想
to continue taking an opportunity to do
继续抓住机会，做
what the Oscars don't and highlight some
奥斯卡奖没有做的事情，重点介绍一些
of the work that's a little more
比较
understated and less showy, but which in
低调、不那么引人注目的作品，但在
my opinion is just as deserving of
我看来，这些作品同样值得
recognition. I've already talked about
认可。 我之前已经谈到过
what Wagner Moura does in this scene
瓦格纳·莫拉在《
from The Secret Agent, but there's
秘密特工》这个场景中的表演，但
another moment a little later that is
稍后还有一个片段，
maybe one of my favorite bits of
也许是我
performance from all of 2025. It plays
2025年最喜欢的表演之一。它
best within the context of the film, but
在电影的语境中才能发挥最佳效果，但
it's another incredible example of a
它也是一个绝佳的例子，
suggests a very rich, layered, and
说明即使没有做太多，也能暗示这些角色非常丰富、多层次和
complicated emotional past for these
复杂的情感过往
characters.
。
The quality of Moura's performance in
莫拉在《秘密特工》中的表演质量堪称
The Secret Agent is in good company. The
一流。
movie as a whole is a master class in
整部电影堪称
great subtle performances. Luciano
精湛表演的典范。 卢西亚诺·
Quaroli as Henrique Gularte, who's sort
夸罗利饰演的恩里克·古拉特是
of the arch-villain of the film, feels
这部电影中的大反派，在我看来，他和
every bit as menacing to me as any other
其他
villain we saw last year. Subtler
我们去年看到的反派一样具有威胁性。 更微妙的
villainy can be difficult, but Quaroli
反派形象可能很难塑造，但夸罗利成功地
pulls off the kind of blatant contempt
展现了那种赤裸裸的蔑视
and hostility that's lightly shrouded
和敌意，这种蔑视和敌意被巧妙地掩盖
within corporate austerity and
在企业严谨和
professionalism that really helps you
专业精神之中，这真正帮助你
understand the righteous anger that
理解了
drives Armando into the situation that
驱使阿曼多陷入
kicks off the film.
影片开篇情境的义愤。
Most of the hype surrounding performance
大部分关于绩效
incentives ended up on Michael B.
奖金的炒作最终都集中在了迈克尔·B·
Jordan, who's incredibly talented and
乔丹身上，他才华横溢，
deserves recognition. But the
理应获得认可。 但
performances in the film that I found
我觉得这部电影中
most magnetic were the supporting roles
最吸引人的表演是
from Wunmi Mosaku and Delroy Lindo.
温米·莫萨库和德尔罗伊·林多的配角表演。
Both of these actors do something with
这两位演员在演绎
these roles that I have always found a
这些角色时，都展现出一种我一直觉得很
little magical. They just seem to show
神奇的特质。 他们仿佛直接
up on the screen as the character,
以角色的身份出现在屏幕上，
feeling like the character's always been
感觉这个角色一直都是
a part of this world. I'm not sure
这个世界的一部分。 我不太清楚
exactly how actors pull this off. I
演员们是如何做到这一点的。 我
think it's often a combination of great
认为，往往是优秀的
casting and a bunch of small, almost
选角和许多细微的、几乎
imperceptible choices that end up giving
难以察觉的选择相结合，最终才使
the character a very lived-in feel.
角色显得非常真实可信。
Lindo especially feels like he just is
林多尤其觉得自己就是
this guy.
这样一个人。
&gt;&gt; You ain't paying no $20 tonight.
你今晚不用付20美元了。
You paying $20, maybe, tonight.
你今晚可能要付20美元。
&gt;&gt; Which is an incredible testament to his
这足以证明他的
ability. But I think the seeming
能力。 但我认为，
effortlessness with which he
他看似毫不费力地
accomplishes this performance undersells
完成这场表演，低估了他
the talent on display here. I'm sure
所展现的才华。 我相信
people are sick of me talking about
大家现在肯定都听腻了我谈论
sentimental value at this point. But I
情感价值这件事了。 但是，如果
without mentioning the performances from
不提及
Renate Reinsve and Stellan Skarsgård.
雷纳特·雷恩斯维和斯特兰·斯卡斯加德的表演，就无法谈论精妙的表演。
Both these actors face a particular
这两位演员在演绎
challenge with these characters in that
这些角色时都面临着特殊的挑战，因为
conflict in the film is their shared
影片中许多紧张和冲突的根源在于他们共同
inability to really open up and express
无法真正敞开心扉，表达
how they feel. You might think that
自己的感受。 你可能会认为
playing a character that's less
扮演一个
emotionally expressive might be an
情感表达较少的角色会更
easier task,
容易，
but you don't want the audience to think
但你不希望观众认为
or feel that the characters aren't
或感觉到角色
actually feeling emotion. You still need
实际上没有情感。 你仍然需要向
to show the audience the layers of
观众展示
emotion that are alive within this
这个角色内心深处鲜活的情感层次
character, all while showing the
，同时还要向观众表明，
audience that they're trying to repress
他们试图压抑
and hide these emotions beneath the
和隐藏这些情感
surface. There are bigger, more dramatic
。 这部电影中还有一些更精彩、更戏剧性的
moments that I could point to in this
时刻，我可以指出这些时刻来
film as examples of what make these
说明这些
performances great. But instead, I want
表演为何如此出色。 但是，我更想
to highlight a few of the very tiny
重点介绍一下影片中一些非常细微的
moments we see throughout the film. Like
瞬间。 就像
with Nora's performance in The Secret
诺拉在《秘密特工》中的表演一样
Agent, we often get a sense of the
，我们常常能感受到
conflict that these characters are
这些角色内心正在
experiencing internally.
经历的冲突。
In moments like this, it's as if we
在这样的时刻，我们
literally see Nora wanting to say more
仿佛能看到诺拉想要说更多的话，
but holding back as these momentary
但却克制住了，
flickers of emotion happen on her face.
她的脸上偶尔闪过一丝情绪。
When Borg looks at a room, we can feel
当博格看到一个房间时，即使我们对
the weighty significance of that room
这个房间一无所知，也能感受到它所蕴含的重大意义
even before we know anything about it.
。
And when he turns and catches sight of
当他转身看到
Nora across the house,
诺拉在房子的另一边时，一丝
the briefest smile tries to peek through
短暂的微笑试图从压在
the sadness weighing him down. Later, he
他心头的悲伤中透出来。 后来，他
asks if she's okay.
问她是否还好。
And we can see suddenly she's posturing
我们可以看到，她突然摆出了
in an almost unnoticeable but kind of
一个几乎难以察觉但又有些
stiff way that seems to indicate a
僵硬的姿势，这似乎表明
defensive shield the character is
该角色正在竖起一道防御屏障
putting up. And in this scene, which
。 在这个场景中，就在
happens not long after she's stormed out
她怒气冲冲地离开
of a meeting with her father,
与父亲的会面后不久，
stiffens her posture when her father
当父亲进来时，她调整姿势并略微僵硬，这透露出
enters gives away her concern about how
她担心
seeing him is going to go. In the brief
见到父亲会如何。 在
exchange that follows, we can see both
接下来的简短交流中，我们可以看到
of them check in with each other as if
他们两人互相确认，仿佛
to say, "Are we good?" While they refuse
在说：“我们没事吧？” 虽然他们在对话中完全拒绝
to acknowledge the situation whatsoever
承认这种情况
[clears throat]
[清嗓子]
explicitly in the dialogue.
。
Hi.
你好。
Something, their relationship, their
某些因素，可能是他们的关系、过往
baggage, their trauma, whatever it is,
经历、创伤等等，
prevents them from being able to just
阻碍了他们
talk openly and outright about these
坦诚地谈论这些
things. So, most of their emotional
事情。 因此，
relationship in this film and the
这部电影中他们之间的大部分情感关系和
dramatic conflict between them is
戏剧冲突都是
communicated through these small pieces
通过这些细微的
of subtext and their reactions,
潜台词、他们的反应、
postures, a look, or how they say a
姿势、眼神或他们说
line.
台词的方式来传达的。
Whether it's the smallest flicker in an
无论是眼神中最细微的闪烁，
eye or the gentle heave of a sigh, this
还是轻轻的叹息，这种
type of performance has always held a
表演方式
special [music] place for me in cinema
在我心中一直占据着电影音乐中一个特殊的地位，
because it's something the medium can do
因为这是电影这种媒介能够做到而
that not many others can. When you can
其他媒介却做不到的事情。 当你能够
make a character larger than life on the
让银幕上的角色超越现实
screen, when you can [music] turn their
，当你能够用音乐将他们的
face into an entire landscape and slow
脸变成一幅完整的风景，并放慢
the story down long enough for the
故事节奏，让
audience to really be able to examine
观众有足够多的时间去仔细观察
that landscape.
这幅风景。
True subtlety in performance can become
表演中真正的微妙之处可以大到
large enough for us to read in a way
让我们能够以一种
that isn't [music] present in many other
在许多其他形式的音乐中不存在的方式去解读
forms.
。
And often, if we're being honest, isn't
坦白地说，很多时候，它甚至根本不
even present in our own lives.
存在于我们自己的生活中。
It's rare we get such a close, intimate,
我们很少有机会如此近距离、深入、
[music] unflinching look at people's
毫不掩饰地观察人们的
emotional landscapes and reactions.
情感世界和反应。
And that's something cinema has a unique
而这正是电影
opportunity [music] to provide.
（音乐）所能提供的独特优势。
It doesn't mean it's the best type of
这并不意味着它是最好的
performance, but it means it's one I
表现形式，但它意味着它是我非常重视的一种表现形式
value highly. I think the bigger, more
。 我认为那些场面宏大、更炫
showy performances are [music] great and
目的表演固然
entertaining, but there's something
精彩纷呈，但
special about the subtle performances
细腻的表演对
for me, and I hope filmmakers and actors
我来说却有着特殊的意义。我希望电影制作人和演员们能够
continue to do the work of providing
继续创作这类表演，
them even if they're not as likely to
即使它们不太可能
win awards.
赢得奖项。
Let me tell you about my sponsor for
让我来介绍一下
this video, Nord VPN. A VPN is a virtual
本视频的赞助商：Nord VPN。  VPN是虚拟
private network, which is a service that
专用网络的简称，它是一种
allows you to send your internet traffic
允许您将互联网流量发送
through another location. And there's a
到其他位置的服务。
lot of reasons you might want to do
你可能有很多理由想这样做
this, but I'm going to highlight two of
，但我会
them for you specifically. The first is
特别为你强调其中两个原因。 首先是
privacy. When you browse the internet
隐私问题。 当您
without a VPN, your traffic is exposed
不使用 VPN 浏览互联网时，您的网络流量将暴露
to your internet service provider. That
给您的互联网服务提供商。 这
makes it easier for you to be tracked by
使得
both companies and even the government,
公司甚至政府更容易追踪你，
and there's unfortunately an increasing
但不幸的是，越来越多的人
number of reasons why you might not want
可能不希望
that. When you use a VPN like Nord VPN,
这样。 使用像 NordVPN 这样的 VPN 时，
your ISP just sees your connection to
您的 ISP 只会看到您与
the VPN and your internet traffic
VPN 的连接，您的互联网流量
remains private. The other huge benefit
将保持私密。  VPN的另一个巨大好处
of a VPN is that it allows you to access
是，它可以让您像身处世界其他地方一样访问
the internet as if you're somewhere else
互联网
in the world. This can help you avoid
。 这可以帮助你避免
price gouging and get better deals on
价格欺诈，并在
things like flights and hotels. It can
机票和酒店等方面获得更优惠的价格。 它还可以
also help you access content more freely
帮助你更自由地访问内容，
if you live in a place where the
如果你居住在
government or corporations have censored
政府或企业审查
or restricted the content that's
或限制
available to you. In addition to the
你所获取的内容的地方。 除了
benefits of a VPN, there's a lot of
VPN 的好处之外，
other Nord specific features that help
Nord 还提供了许多其他特有的功能，可以帮助
protect your privacy and security
保护您的在线隐私和安全
online. It's very affordable. I've been
。 价格非常实惠。 我
working with and using Nord VPN for
使用 Nord VPN 已经很多
years and you can get an exclusive deal
年了，如果你访问 nordvpn.com/tflight，就​​能获得独家优惠，还能
along with 4 months extra when you go to
额外获得 4 个月的使用时间
nordvpn.com/tflight. You can click the
。 您可以点击
below or again go to nordvpn.com/tflight
下方说明中的链接，或者再次访问 nordvpn.com/tflight
to get that exclusive deal. Thanks again
获取该独家优惠。 再次感谢
to Nord VPN for sponsoring this video.
Nord VPN赞助本视频。
&gt;&gt; [snorts]
[嗤笑]